Guide to the International Socialists Records TAM.088
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Socialists Records
1970-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Socialists (U.S.)
TAM.088
0.75 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
International Socialists (IS), a group with its roots in American Trotskyism and the Young People's Socialist League, was founded in 1969, as the result of several Independent Socialist Clubs merging. IS publications include: Labor Notes(1979- ); International Socialist(1969-70), Workers Power(1970-79), and Changes(1979-85). In 1984, IS merged with two other left groupings to form Solidarity. The collection contains minutes, position papers, reports, various convention materials, and miscellaneous documents. The bulk of the material concerns internal political debates and organizational tendencies.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
International Socialists (IS), a Third Camp-oriented group with historical and organizational roots in American Trotskyism and the Young People's Socialist League, was founded in 1969, as the result of the merger of several Independent Socialist Clubs (the first was formed in Berkeley, California in 1964). IS concentrated on work in the labor movement, playing an important role in the Teamster reform movement, and the monthly periodical Labor Notes, 1979- (established and directed by IS members), along with its annual conference, have become a leading center for militant labor officials and rank and file unionists. Other IS periodical titles were: International Socialist(1969-70), Workers Power(1970-79), and Changes(1979-85). In 1984 IS merged with Workers Power (itself the 1979 result of one of several 1970s splits from IS) and Socialist Unity to form Solidarity, a revolutionary socialist organization. For more information, see "Independent Socialist Clubs/International Socialists," in Encyclopedia of the American Left (1998) pp. 348-351.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains various IS documents, including minutes of its Executive, National and National Action committees, position papers, reports (including those of the National Secretary), various convention materials, and miscellaneous documents. The bulk of the material concerns internal political debates and organizational tendencies, including the 1973 expulsion of the Revolutionary Tendency, whose members, led by Sy Landy and others, went on to found the Revolutionary Socialist League.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Inventory
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1980.002.
Correspondence.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Socialists -- United States.; Student movements.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Solidarity (Organization: U.S.); Revolutionary Socialist League; International Socialists (U.S.); Young People's Socialist League
- Inventory
  - Miscellaneous Undated (1) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Undated (2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Convention Material, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NAC Minutes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NAC Minutes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NC Minutes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Convention Material, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NAC Minutes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - National Secretary Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Constitution, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Convention Material, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - EC Motions & Communications, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Convention Material, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - EC Motions & Communications, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NC Reports, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Convention Material, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - EC Motions & Communications, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Secretary Communications, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Position Papers, Reports, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)